[MUSIC]
Today I'm going to introduce
you to the Android Platform.
I'll start by giving you an overview
of the Android Platform, and
the components that make it up.
And then I'll present each
of these components and
discuss how they help developers
build great mobile applications.
So let's get started.
The Android platform is a software stack,
and it was designed primarily, but
not exclusively, to support mobile
devices such as phones and tablets.
And this stack has several layers,
going all the way from low-level operating
system services that manage the device
itself, up to sample applications,
things like the phone dialer, the contacts
database, and the web browser.
Android also comes with
a software developers kit, or
SDK, which is used to create
Android applications.
And finally, there's tons of
documentation, tutorials, blogs, and
examples that you can use to improve
your own understanding of Android, and
I encourage you to take advantage
of all these resources.
Now this graphic represents
the Android software stack.
And as you can see,
it's organized into several layers.
At the bottom there's
the Linux kernel layer.
Above that, there are system libraries and
the Android run time system.
Above that, there's a rich
application framework player to
support the development
of new applications,.
And at the very top, Android provides
some standard applications, again,
things like the phone dialer, the web
browser, and the contacts database.
So let's look at each of
these layers in detail,
starting with the Linux kernel layer.
The Linux kernel layer is the lowest layer
of software in the Android platform.
This layer provides the core services that
any Android computing device will rely on.
Android's Linux kernel,
just like any Linux kernel, provides
generic operating system services.
For example,
it provides a permissions architecture so
that you can restrict access to data and
resources to only those processes
that have the proper authorizations.
It supports memory and process management,
so that multiple processes can
run simultaneously without
interfering with each other.
It handles low-level details of file and
network I/O.
And it also allows device drivers to
be plugged in so that Android can
communicate with a wide range of
low-level hardware components that
are often coupled to computing devices,
things like memory and radios and cameras.
In addition to the common services
supported by any Linux kernel,
Android's Linux kernel also includes
several Android-specific components.
For example,
Android's Linux kernel includes its own
power management services because mobile
devices often run on battery power.
It provides its own memory sharing and
memory management features, because
mobile devices often have limited memory.
And Android's Linux kernel also includes
its own inter-process communication
mechanism called the binder, which allows
multiple processes to share data and
services in sophisticated ways.
And of course, this is just a few
of the Android-specific features.
There are many others as well.
Next layer up includes
a variety of system libraries.
These libraries are typically
written in C and
C++, and for that reason they are often
referred to as the native libraries.
And these native libraries
handle a lot of the core,
performance-sensitive activities
on your device,
things like quickly rendering web
pages and updating the display.
And for example, Android has its own
System C Library, which implements
the standard OS system calls, which do
things like process and thread creation,
mathematical computations,
memory allocation, and much more.
There's the Surface Manager,
for updating the display.
A media framework, for
playing back audio and video files.
Webkit, for rendering and
displaying web pages.
OpenGL for high performance graphics.
And SQLite for
managing in-memory relational databases.
In addition to the system libraries, this
layer also includes the Android Runtime,
which supports writing and
running Android applications.
And there are two components in
the Android Runtime that we'll talk
about today, the core Java libraries and
the Dalvik Virtual Machine.
Let's talk about each
of those one at a time.
Now first, Android applications
are typically written in
the Java programming language.
And to make it easier
to write applications,
Android provides a number of
reusable Java building blocks.
For instance, the Java and Java X, or Java
extensions packages include basic software
for things like common data structures,
concurrency mechanisms and file I/O.
The Android packages have software
that's specific to the life cycle of
mobile applications.
The ORG packages support various
internet or web operations.
And the JUnit packages support
the unit testing of applications.
The second part of the Android Runtime
is the Dalvik Virtual Machine.
The Dalvik virtual machine is
the software that actually executes
Android applications.
Now as I just told you, Android
applications are typically written in
Java, so you might have assumed that
since they're written in Java they would
probably run on a standard Java virtual
machine, but in fact that's not the case.
What typically happens is that
developers first write their
applications in the Java
programming language.
Then a Java compiler will
compile the Java source code
files into multiple Java bytecode files.
Next, a tool called DX transforms the Java
bytecodes into a single file of a
different bytecode format called DEX, and
this bytecode file is
usually called classes.dex.
Next the DEX file is packaged with
other application resources and
installed on the device.
And finally when the user
launches the application,
the Dalvik Virtual Machine will
then execute the classes.dex file.
Now the reason for doing all this
is that the Dalvik Virtual Machine,
unlike the the Java Virtual Machine,
was specifically designed to run in
the resource-constrained environment
which is typical of mobile devices.
Now when I say resource-constrained,
what I mean is that compared
to a typical desktop device,
the typical mobile device is less
powerful and more limited in many ways.
For example, it will probably have
a slower CPU, less memory and
a limited battery life.
So if you're interested in finding out
more about the Dalvik Virtual Machine
itself then I recommend you take
a look at this video, Dalvik Virt,
VM Internals by Dan Bornstein of Google.
The next layer in the Android software
stack is the application framework.
The application framework
contains reusable software that
many mobile applications
are likely to need.
For example, as we'll see in a minute,
the View system contains common graphical
elements, things like buttons, and
icons, that many applications
include in their user interfaces.
Let's take a deeper look at
some of these components.
One application framework
component is the Package Manager.
The Package Manager is
essentially a database that
keeps track of all the applications
currently installed on your device.
So here's the home screen of my phone.
When I click on the Launcher icon,
the phone shows me a bunch of icons,
each one representing an application
package that's stored on my phone.
The Package Manager stores information
about these applications, and
that's useful for several reasons.
For example, it allows applications
to find and contact each other so
that one application can share data
with another application, or so
that one application can
request services from another.
Another application framework
component is the Window Manager.
The Window Manager,
as the name suggests, manages the many
windows that comprise applications.
Here I'm launching the Browser
application, which appears as two windows.
At the top,
there's the System Notification bar,
which displays various status indicators
that tell the user about things
like WiFi signal strength, remaining
battery power, and the current time.
There's also a Main Application window,
that in this case is showing
the current web page.
An application can also
use various sub windows,
such as when it shows menus or dialogs.
As I mentioned earlier, the application
framework also contains the View System.
The View System contains many common
graphical user interface elements,
such as icons, text entry boxes,
buttons, and much more.
Let's take a look at
the phone application.
As you can see,
the phone application's top level user
interface is organized as a set of tabs.
And each tab corresponds
to a different user
interface that supports
a different set of tasks.
The Phone tab shows me a phone dialer.
The Call Log tab shows a list of
recent incoming and outgoing calls.
And the Contacts tab shows
a list of stored contacts.
Now as I just said,
when I select the Phone tab, I'm shown a
user interface that mimics a phone keypad.
That keypad is made up of view system
components, things like buttons and
text views.
And then the application will listen as I
press these buttons and then respond by
writing the corresponding digits to a text
view to show me what number I'm dialing.
The next application framework
component is the Resource Manager.
This component manages the non-compiled
resources that make up an application,
things like strings, graphics,
and user interface layout files.
And to give you example of
non-compiled resources,
let's go back to the phone
application again.
Now this tab has some English words on it,
and that's fine because I speak English.
But Android is available around the world,
it's not limited to English speakers, and
so it's important that we have an easy
way to customize applications for
other languages.
And one way that Android
supports that is that,
that it lets you define
strings in multiple languages.
For example, the phone
application has a string file for
Italian words as well as one for
English words.
So if you speak Italian, then you can
go into the Settings application and
select Italian as your default language.
Now, if I go back and rerun the phone
application, you'll see that Android will
use the appropriate Italian words
rather than the English words.
And, of course, you can do this for
as many languages as makes sense for
your application.
Another application framework
component is the Activity Manager.
Now at a high level,
Android activities often correspond
to a single user interface screen.
Applications are then
created by stringing together
multiple activities through
which the user can navigate.
The Activity Manager helps to coordinate
and support that kind of navigation.
So suppose I want to listen to some music.
So here I'll click on the Launcher
icon to show my applications.
From there,
I can click on the Music Player icon.
And that will start an activity that
brings up a user interface screen
showing the music I have on my device,
in this case sorted by artist.
I can select an artist, and
see the albums by that artist.
I can select one album by clicking on it.
And this starts another activity that
brings up another user interface screen,
showing the songs in
the album I just selected.
And now if I hit the Back button,
I can go back to the last activity,
and for example,
I can choose a different album.
Now I can click on a specific song in that
album, and yet another activity starts up
that brings up yet another user interface
screen, allowing me to play this song.
Another application framework component
implements Content Providers.
Content Providers are essentially
databases that allow applications to
store and share structured information.
For example, here we see that the phone
application can access stored
contact information and
use it to dial a phone number.
And it can do that because
the contact information is stored in
a Content Provider.
And even better, Content Providers are
designed to work across applications so
not only can the phone dialer use
the contact information, but so
can the MMSM, messaging application and
so can various social media applications.
Let's take a look.
So going back to the phone application,
I can select the Contact tab to
access stored contact information.
I can select one of the contacts
to quickly dial that contact.
Now as I said, I can do that
because contact information is
stored in a Content Provider.
And again, even better, Content Providers
are designed to work across applications.
So not only can the phone dialer use
the contacts, but so can the MMS messaging
application, and so can Twitter, Facebook,
my email readers, and things like that.
The next application framework
component is the Location Manager.
The Location Manager allows
applications to receive location and
movement information,
such as that generated by the GPS system.
And this allows applications to
perform context-specific tasks,
things like finding directions
from the current location.
Now here I'm calling up
the Google Maps application,
which queries the Location Manager for
my current location, and
then shows a map of the area
around that current location.
The last application framework
component I'll talk about today
is the Notification Manager.
The Notification Manager allows
applications to place information in
the Notification bar, for example,
to let users know that
certain events have occurred.
For example, suppose I want to
send my wife an MMS message.
And let's suppose that at right at
this minute, she's writing an email or
making a phone call or whatever.
So although she probably wants to know
that I've sent her an MMS message,
she might not want that
to disrupt her right now.
Well, Android handles this
with a Notification Manager.
And the way that works is that there's
some software running on her phone
that's always listening for
incoming MMS messages.
When one arrives, that software uses
the Notification Manager to place
an icon in her phone's Notification bar.
And that's shown as
a little smiley face icon.
And I've whited out some of the,
some of the information there for privacy.
Now when she's ready,
she can pull down on the Notification bar,
which then shows more information
about the specific notification.
And if she clicks on that notification,
the MMS application will start up and
she can read and
hopefully respond to my message.
The last layer of the Android software
stack is the Application layer.
As I said earlier, Android comes
with some built-in applications, and
these include things like the home screen,
the phone dialer, the web browser,
an email reader, and more.
And one of the things that's really
nice about Android is that none of
these apps is hard-coded into the system.
If you have a better app,
you can substitute your app for
any of these standard apps.