[MUSIC]
The IDE also comes with a debugger that
gives developers powerful tools for
examining the internal state
of a running application.
And this can be useful of course when
you have a bug in your application and
you're not sure exactly what's causing it.
So let's use the debugger
to examine an application.
Here I'm showing you a simple Android
application I've named, the answer.
And this app is supposed to show you
the answer to life, the universe and
everything which, as The Hitchhiker's
Guide to the Galaxy tells us, is 42.
As you can see however,
instead of displaying 42,
this app says, we may never know.
So clearly there's a bug somewhere.
Let's use the debugger
to track that bug down.
And here we are in the IDE.
First I'll open up the answer application
and show you it's source code.
Now, the truth is that this
is a pretty silly program and
a bug would be fairly obvious once
you've looked at the code a bit.
But my goal here is to show you how the
debugger works, so just between you and
us, let's pretend that we
don't know what's going on.
And you can see that there's
an array called mAnswers through
which the program will search looking for
the answer 42.
Now here's the onCreate method which is
the starting point when this class is
executed.
Inside onCreate there's a call
to a method called findAnswer.
And the code for the findAnswer
method is listed down below.
Now findAnswer is supposed to
search the mAnswers array and
return the number 42 if it's in there or
minus one, if it's not.
Now going back up, the program stores
findAnswers return value in the variable
val, and then uses the variable to
compute a string called output.
Then finally,
the program calls the setText method to
display the output string on the screen.
So let's say that,
since I don't know where the bug is,
I decide to debug this program.
The first thing I'll do then is to set
a break point that stops the program
when it enters the onCreate method.
Now, instead of running the program,
I'll debug it by selecting Run, and
then debug app from the application bar.
And I could have also just
typed Ctrl+D as well.
I'll click OK to run this on my phone.
Now when the application reaches onCreate,
it stops and
shows me the debug view with the current
line highlighted in the source code.
At this point, I'll step through the code
line by line, examining the program state.
To step forward, I'll select
Step Over from the debugger toolbar,
which advances the program one line.
Let me do that a few more times.
And I'm now at the line
that calls findAnswer.
And store the return result
in the variable val.
Let me step over this line.
And once I step over this line, you'll
see that the value of the variable val
is now minus 10,
which is already a problem.
It should have been 42.
Now if I advance again, I see that the
output string is set to We may never know.
Okay, so the problem is certainly
down in the findAnswer method, so
let's look more closely
at the findAnswer method.
To do that, I'll put a break
point at the findAnswer method,
and then restart the application.
Now this time when the application stops
at onCreate I'll just hit the resume
button which let's the application
continue executing until the findAnswer
break point is hit.
And I can now step forward in this method
and examine the values of different
variables to determine that
42 is indeed in the array,
and that findAnswer sees it, but
considers it the wrong answer.
Anyway, as I'm sure you've figured
out long ago, the problem is that I'm
accidentally checking for
not equals rather than for equals, equals.
So, I'll fix that.
And now I'll start over.
And this time we'll see
the correct behavior.
And there it goes.
And yes, the answer to life,
the universe and everything is indeed 42.
And I think the debuggers help most
when you have a reasonably good
idea of where your problem is, and you
can focus in on just a few lines of code.
But, in many other situations,
that kind of low level instruction by
instruction examination that debuggers
are so good at, is a lot less helpful.
Instead it may be better
to use more general tools
that instrument your system and
let you monitor its behavior over time.
Android provides a number
of these monitoring tools
in its Dalvik Debug Monitor Service,
or DDMS.
Now today I'll talk about
just four of these tools.
The file explorer, for
viewing a devices file system, logcat, for
logging and displaying runtime events,
traceview for displaying method
execution traces and the hierarchy viewer
for examining user interface layouts.
Let's look at these tools and
see how you can access them from the IDE.
First let's start the device monitor,
which exposes a number of panes and
buttons for accessing the DDMS tools.
Now here you can see a devices pane.
That shows the devices that
are currently connected and
shows a list of processes
running on those devices.
The first tool we'll look at,
is the file explorer.
This view shows you the files on
the selected devices file system.
For example, here we see that this device
has a slash data, slash data directory,
in which applications typically
store persistent data.
This device also has an external memory
card mounted under slash storage,
slash SD card.
And there are some standard
directories there for
storing music, and
movies, and other things.
The next tool I'll talk
about shows the logcat view.
Android logs many events by default.
And that is, as the software runs,
it spits out information about the things
that are happening on the device.
And this information is stored and
can be displayed in the logcat view.
Android also provides methods that let
developers log their own information.
Another tool is called traceview.
Traceview allows you to trace
the methods your application calls.
Let's do this for the anstrap
application I showed you earlier.
So this is the source code for
the application.
To simplify my demonstration I'll first
put a breakpoint in the onCreate method.
And now I'll start debugging it.
As you can see,
it stopped at the breakpoint.
And now when I start profiling,
so I'll open the DDMS
tool window by typing Cmd+6,
or Alt+6 in Windows.
And then I'll click on the button
that shows a clock and
displays the text, Start Method Tracing.
Now I'll return to the debug view,
and resume the application.
I want to program run for a while, and
now, I'll return back to the DDMS tool
window, and press that same button, but
this time, stop the method profiling.
And this point, traceview will
process the trace information, and
show it to me graphically.
The traceview display has two panels.
One is a timeline view showing
the method call stack across time.
The other is a textual
view which shows execution
statistics such as the number
of times a method was called and
the amount of time spent exclusively in
that method, and the amount of time spent
in that method including any time spent
in methods called from the current one.
Additionally, you can search for
a particular method by typing Cmd+F or
Ctrl+F.
For instance, let's search for
our old friend, findAnswer.
Now here I'll start to type in its name.
And you can see that the methods are
filtered until only findAnswer is left.
And now I can zoom and pan on
the timeline to see more information, and
surrounding context.
The last tool I'll talk about
is the UI hierarchy viewer.
This tool allows you to examine your
application's user interface and
see how it's organized.
For example, let's look again at
the Hello Android application.
First, let's run
Once it's up and running,
go to the menu bar, and
click on the Android
device monitor window.
And this will bring up the device monitor.
And at this point,
you can select the device on
which the application is running.
And then click on the Window
> Open Perspective, and
then Hierarchy View,
to open a hierarchy viewer.
Go to the Windows panel and
double-click the entry corresponding to,
to the Hello Android application.
And it's the one that has
the words Hello Android in it.
Now double-clicking on this entry
should bring up a graphical
representation of
Hello Android's user interface.
Which like most user interfaces
is organized as a tree.
For instance,
there's an outer most application window
which holds the entire user interface.
And it contains two children.
A title or action bar.
And then the larger tangular body
where the application is seen,
each of these in turn,
contain further elements.
So let's look at some of these,
some of these other elements.
When I click on the outer most window,
I see what that entire window looks like,
and I can inspect detailed
information about it.
Such as its layout parameters, which
shows for example how big the window is,
in pixels.
The region occupied by each element is
shown in a layout view in the bottom right
corner.
Now, for instance, I can see this
information for the title bar.
And I can see the same information for
the body.
And for the text view it contains.