[MUSIC]
Today we're going to talk about
the Android Development Environment,
an integrated set of tools to help you
create your own Android applications.
In our last lesson,
I introduced you to the Android platform.
I talked about how the Android
platform is a software stack for
building and running mobile applications.
And if you've used an Android device,
to write email,
to take photos, to get directions to
some location, to play games, and so
on, then you've seen the Android platform
in action and you know what it can do.
So the next question is,
how can you use the Android platform
to write your own Android apps.
Well one part of the answer, is that you
need to learn the details of the Android
platform itself, and in fact that's
what we'll do throughout this class.
Another part of the answer though,
is that you need to learn and
master the tools that allow you to
make use of the Android platform
in order to create new applications.
And that's what we're
going to focus on today.
The tools that I'm talking about
are called
the Android Development Environment, and
you should think of them as your workbench
for creating Android applications.
And like any skilled craftsperson, the
more comfortable you are with your tools,
the easier it's going to be
to produce top quality work.
In this lesson,
we'll cover several topics.
First I'll talk about downloading the
development environment, or Android SDK,
including the Android Studio
Integrated Development Environment, or
IDE, and assorted Android Developer Tools.
And then, I'll show you
the Android Studio IDE in action, and
together we'll create a very
simple Android application.
After that, I'll show you some specific
tools, such as the Android Emulator,
which allows you to run Android
apps without a physical device.
And then I'll show you how to use
the debugger to help you diagnose eventual
problems with your applications.
And finally,
I'll show you a variety of other tools
designed to help you further
perfect your applications.
Before you get started, make sure you
have a supported operating system.
For Windows, these include Windows 7,
Windows 8, Windows Vista, and
Windows Server 2003.
For Mac, you'll need Mac OS X,
10.8.5, up to 10.9.
And for Linux,
several distributions should work, but
the Android SDK is tested on Ubuntu 10.04.
And you can see the Androids developers
website for more information about this.
And you should also make sure that you
have the Java Development Kit Version
7 installed.
Again, check the following website for
more information.
Now Google generally recommends
that your development machine
meet the following specs.
It should have a minimum of 2 gigabytes
of RAM, but 4 gigabytes is recommended.
It should have at least 1
gigabyte of storage for
the Android SDK,
emulator system images, and caches.
And it should also have at least
400 megabytes of free disc space
when it's running.
Oh, and it should also have a minimum
screen resolution of 1280 x 800.
So now you're ready to get started.
First, you'll need to download and
install the Android SDK.
And I suggest that you do this now.
And that way you can follow
along with my examples
while you watch the rest of this lesson.
You can find the SDK
at the URL shown here.
Let me also point you to a short video
put together by our friends at Amazon.
The video is available at this link.
And it'll walk you through the entire
process of downloading and
installing the Android SDK.
Now once installed, the Android SDK
provides you with several things.
First, it has at least one version of
the Android platform, including libraries,
reusable software tools,
and documentation.
It also includes the Android Studio IDE,
which includes a number of tools that'll
help you develop, run, test,
and debug your Android apps.
And it also has a system image for
the emulator.
So, you can run and
debug your Android apps without
needing to have an actual device.
In our last lesson, we talked about
the Android platform in detail.
So today, we'll focus on the other
three elements one by one.
But before we do that,
let's take a look at a very simple
Android App called Hello Android.
Here I'm showing my phone's home screen.
First, I'll click on the launcher icon and
then I'll click on the Hello Android icon,
to launch the application.
The application starts and
displays the words hello world.
Now that's about as simple as it gets,
but let's walk through the process
of writing this Hello Android
application Using the IDE.
Now this my IDE opened to full screen.
Let's start by creating a new
Android application project.
One way to do that is to go to the File
menu, then New, then New Project,
and once you do this, you'll see a series
of dialog boxes that ask you for
information about your application.
On the first screen let's enter
HelloAndroid for the application name.
Where it asks for a Company Domain,
I'm using examples.course.
The IDE will use that to compute
the package name for the application.
And here you can see that it
reverses the company domain and
then tacks on the application name,
all in lower case.
So, in this case, you see the package
name is course.examples.helloandroid.
And the idea here is that
package names created this way
are less likely to conflict with
the package names of other applications
that might end up on the same device.
Now go ahead and hit Next.
Now this screen asks you what kind
of devices you want this application
to run on.
Here I'll stick with Phone and Tablet.
And I'll choose API level 21,
which corresponds to Android
5.0 as the oldest platform
this app will run on.
You can also see that at this time very
few android devices are running API,
level 21 or newer.
So in practice you might want to
chose a lower API level.
Now click on Next.
This dialog is asking what kind of
UI template files I'd like the IDE
to pre-build for me.
Here I'll keep it simple, and
I'll go with a single Blank Activity.
Again, I'll click on the Next button.
And the next dialogue
asks how I want to name
some of the application's
source code file.
I'll just accept the defaults here,
and then I'll click Finish.
Now the IDE will generate
the application's source code and
layout files.
And once it's finished, the IDE displays
a file called activity_main.xlm,
which defines the application's
user interface layout.
And based on the contents of this file,
the IDE will show you
whatever it can about how this
application will look when it runs.
As you can see here,
this app will display a simple
screen with the words hello world.
Let's also take a quick look at
the source code for this application.
So first I'll open up
the file MainActivity.java.
And that opens up an editor window
showing the contents of the file.
Now I won't talk too much about
this source code right now.
Except to say that when
this application runs,
the onCreate method of
this class will be called.
And that code will set up and display
the application's user interface screen.
So let's run this code
to see what happens.
Now one way to run an application, is to
click on, Run in the application bar.
Then select, Run app.
And you could also just type in
the keyboard sho, shortcut, Ctrl+R,
to run the app as well.
Now a dialog box pops up,
asking where to run this application.
In this case, I only have my phone
connected, so I'll choose that.
And now we wait while the application
is copied to the phone, and then run.
And there you have it, your first
Android application running on a device.
Now the phone I just used is a Nexus 4.
But let's suppose that I'd like to test
out this app on a different phone,
say the Galaxy Nexus.
But I don't have one of those phones.
In that case, rather than run out and
buy a new Galaxy Nexus,
I can just run HelloAndroid on an emulated
galaxy Nexus using the Android emulator.
In order to do that, I first need to
create the emulated phone instance that I
will use inside the emulator.
And these emulated phone instances are
called Android Virtual Devices, or AVDs.
So let's go back to the IDE and
set up an Android virtual device
corresponding to a Galaxy Nexus.
So now we're back in the IDE.
First, I'll go to the tool bar and
launch the Android Virtual Device Manager.
It's a bit hard to see here, but look for
the icon that shows an Android
in front of a device.
Clicking that will display a dialogue
box showing existing virtual devices and
allowing you to make new ones.
Let's create a new virtual device.
To do that,
click on the Create Virtual Device button,
which will bring up a new dialogue box.
And I'll start by picking
the Galaxy Nexus device definition.
And then I'll click Next.
Now I'll pick a system image for
the device.
And in this case, let's use a Lollipop or
Android 5.1.1 image that
also has the Google APIs.
I'm picking this image because it
includes apps such as Google Maps
which I plan to use later in this lesson.
Now, I'll click Next.
And here under AVD Name, you can give this
new virtual device any name you want,
but I'll stick with the defaults here.
You can also click on
Show Advanced Settings to do things like
including a front or
back facing camera, or
changing the size of the device's
SD card and things like that.
Now, I'll hit the Finish button.
And the new AVD will eventually
show up in the list.
Now you can click on
that to start that AVD.
And at this point, you may need to wait
while the virtual device boots up.
I'll come back when it's done.
Okay, and there's the home screen
of an emulated Galaxy Nexus.
Now that the emulated Galaxy Nexus
is running, let's return to the IDE.
This time I'll install and
run HelloAndroid on the emulated phone,
rather than on a physical device.
So just like we did before,
click Run and then Run app.
And a dialog box pops up asking
you which device to use.
This time,
instead of selecting an actual device,
I'll select the virtual
device that we just created.
And I'll click OK.
The IDE will install the application on
the virtual device and then run it.
And here you go, HelloAndroid,
running on the emulator.
Now as you can see, it's pretty much the
same as what we saw on my actual device.
But of course, the styling's
a bit different because my actual
device is a Nexus 4, running Android 5.0,
while this virtual device represents
a Galaxy Nexus, running Android 5.1.1.
So today I've shown you that
you can build applications,
like HelloAndroid on a natural device,
inside an emulator, or both.
And there are pluses and
minuses with each approach.
For example, the benefits of using
an emulator include that emulators
are cheaper than actual devices.
You don't have to buy all the devices
that you may want to test on.
Also, unlike a phone, the emulator
allows you to easily configure hardware
characteristics like the size of the SD
card you have, the display size, and
whether the device has a track ball.
Also, any modifications you make
are isolated to the emulated device, so
you don't have to worry that your testing
will mess up your phone or its data.
On the other hand, emulators have
some real downsides as well.
In particular,
the Android emulator is really slow.
And that can be frustrating when you're
trying to rapidly experiment and
tune your app, and you have to wait for
the emulator to start up and run.
Also, some features are not
well supported by the emulator.
For instance, there's no support for
Bluetooth connectivity and no support for
connecting accessories to
the emulator via USB cables.
Also, some software features aren't
available by default in the emulator, so
certain applications may not run on it.
And finally, at the end of the day,
the emulator is not the device.
You can't really know how your
app is going to look and perform
on an actual device just by looking
at how it performs in the emulator.
So let's take a look at some
of the advanced features
that the Android Emulator does support.
For instance, you can configure
the emulator to emulate the speed and
latency of different cellular networks.
You can configure the emulator to emulate
different battery states, such as whether
you're running low on battery power,
or currently charging the device.
And you can also inject mock location
coordinates to make testing of location
aware applications easier.
And typically you'd use these
features to help you test code that
must respond to the environment or
environmental events.
For instance, applications are often
designed to do different things
depending on the battery level.
Let's take a look.
Let me show you how easy this is.
Here, I'm showing a terminal window and
an emulator running a virtual device.
In the terminal window, I'll use
telnet to connect to the emulator.
And you can see the port number
on which the emulator's listening
in the emulator window's title bar.
In this case that's 5554.
So I'll type telnet localhost 5554.
And now I'll set the network
characteristics to
emulate a slower edge network,
network speed edge.
And notice that the cellular
network status icon
in the notification bar Has now changed.
Now I'll change it back to 3G
by typing network speed full.
And now I'll change the battery
status to reflect a phone
that is running low on battery,
power capacity 10.
And again, you can see that the battery
status indicator in the notification bar
has changed to reflect
the lower battery level.
And you can also see that the device
is currently plugged in and charging.
Well I can also change the charging status
to indicate the the phone is not plugged
in, power status not-charging.
And you can see that the charging
status indicator has gone away.
I can also set the emulator's
location to Washington D.C.
by typing in the following command,
geo fix minus 77.04 38.897.
If I now open up the maps application,
you can see that it shows my
location as Washington, DC.
The Android emulator also allows you
to emulate networked interactions,
such as receiving a phone call or
an SMS message.
Back in the terminal window, I'll
reconnect to the emulator over telnet.
And then I'll give the emulator
a command which will cause it to
emulate an incoming SMS message.
And that command is sms send,
then the sender's phone number,
3015555555.
And then the text message itself,
this is a text message.
Now keep your eye on the emulator window
to see what happens when I hit Return,
here goes.
Now as you can see, the emulator's
notification bar, now contains an icon
Indicating that the emulated phone
just received my SMS message.
And we can pull down on the notification
bar to start the messaging
application to take a closer
look at the SMS message.
Android even allows two emulators
to interact with each other.
Here I'm showing two
emulator instances running.
In one,
I'll open the phone application and
start to dial the number of the second.
The number of the second
emulator is the port number shown
at the top of that emulator window,
in this case, 5554.
And now you see that the second
emulator has received the call and
is ringing its user.
[SOUND] So I'll pick up the incoming
call in the second emulator.
And you can see that the emulator's
interface has now changed to
reflect that the call is connected.
Now, if one of the parties
hits the hold button,
that will also be reflected
in both phone applications.
And once the users are done with the call,
I can hang up.
[SOUND] And both emulators show that
the call has been disconnected.
And of course, that's just a few of
the things you can do with the emulator.
There are many other
interesting features as well.
And if you want to know more, I recommend
you take a look at the emulator
page on the Android developer's website.